[music]
>> Welcome to Business Central launch
edition 2026 release wave one and
welcome to the session introduction to
expense management. My name is Isaac
Sattelmeier and I'm product manager in a
Business Central.
So,
>> [sighs]
>> expense management and why did we start
with expense management? This is long
time functional gap in a Business
Central.
So, what you could do earlier? You could
either choose one of ISV solutions or
use very limited capabilities. By very
limited capabilities, I mean you could
use general employee journals and
eventually purchase invoices in some
cases if if this is related to invoice.
But in general, it was not about expense
agent. This is not about expense
management minimum.
So, what we decided? We decided to build
new functionality but created as a
AI-driven.
So, we didn't just wanted to create new
new feature. We wanted to create new
feature but completely AI-driven. So,
what we succeed?
Our recommendation, use expense
management as a expense agent. So, use
with the agent. And every agent will
provide much much more functionalities
and much more automations. But
even if you decide not to use agent,
maybe you are currently in a region
where agent is not enabled or you have
some another reason, you can use some
basic functionalities in expense
management without using agent. But
again, our high recommendation is to use
agent because you will get away more
functionalities.
When you look into expense management
capabilities without agent
and you compare with a recording where
we had a agent, this is way smaller. But
you still have options to collect
expenses, to itemize, reconcile, expense
report create,
approve reimbursement and post
reimbursement. So, you have all these
workflows. Workflow is configured
and enabled but with the less
functionalities. So,
in a case of expense management without
agent, you will not have expenses. You
can start to collect expenses directly
creating expense report. So, you need to
start with expense report and then you
can handle with expenses there. You can
add itemization, of course, if you you
can add guest if you have
some
entertainment event or something like
that. So, these features will be covered
but you cannot start earlier than
expense report. So, you need to start
with expense report and then to add
another features.
So, some automations we have there
with the attachments, with the
extraction, OCR, they are not covered.
So, in the most of cases, you can
prepare expense report, you can add your
expenses directly in expense report
lines, you can check against some rule
of validations, approve it and post it.
So, this is what you can get if you do
not use agent.
So, first I want to compare overview
high-level architecture with the agent
and with no agent. So, when agent
work on behalf of employee, what do you
have? You have expense user
and user can be part of teams.
We have expense teams. So,
in teams you will know who is manager.
So, easier for approval setup. But the
main person is expense user. Expense
user will create expense
based on LLM
and auto categorization. But then
we will continue to receive another
directions
information from another directions.
Currently, this is not in public preview
but we will have connection with the
credit card provider. So, you can
collect information from from credit
cards and reconcile with existing
expenses.
When we have everything approved
everything will be added into
automatically into expense report. It
will pass through approval process and
you will get posted expense reports and
all other applicable entries. And of
course, we have a lot of setup rules,
posting groups, locations and so on and
so on. So, to support all these
changes. If you look into approval, you
will see small
piece of paper there as a document
policies. So, we have additional model
if you're using with agents. We have
human language explaining policies. So,
agent can check if everything what you
apply there is fit with your company
policies. So, this is something what
exists only in agent. So, now if you
look what is in a basic high-level
architecture with no agent, you can see
okay, we have expense users but you can
create only expense report and finish
regular approval process and post
expense report. This is what we have.
Okay, we have setup
rules, posting groups and so on. So, you
have these basic things
straightforward approval. Approval
already exists in a Business Central and
you must be Business Central user. So,
you cannot handle if you're not Business
Central user.
So, this is a base difference. So, what
we have inside the Business Central? I
mentioned a few time rules.
You can use if again with no
agent. With agent, we have policies, we
have much
more complexity about rules. But here in
a Business Central without agent, you
have only rules. So, this is about
straightforward information about
amounts. You can say what is the
maximum, minimum amount. Some threshold
where this is where this required
justification or it will not allow to
spend more than some amount and so on.
This is it require absolute accuracy.
It can be used for per diem, for
example, rules
as a daily rate. So, you have this
minimum, maximum and other options but
you have daily rate option. So, you can
use this for configuration of per diem.
And if we talk about per diem, what you
need to have for per diem calculation
per diem setup, sorry. You need to have
a created country region code and then
in a set set up expense location, you
need to configure city and province.
What does it mean?
You can have one per diem amount per
country. So, all good. You just need to
configure country region code and
configure
what will be amount for this
expense location. But
why we do not use a regular location?
You can have different amounts for per
diem based on different places where
you're traveling. For example, you can
have in UK for London much higher per
diem for other parts of UK
smaller amounts. So, you can involve
city, you can involve province, you can
decide how you want to split and how you
want to different your per diem amounts.
Once when you have configure
expense locations, you will create a
rule. In this rule, you need to decide
this is per diem add expense location
and the currency code because you can
have different currency codes related to
per diem in different countries. And
then in rule conditions, you need to
enter daily rate and in a value, you
will enter per diem amount. So, if you
are traveling to the United States and
for all all states and all cities there,
you need to configure expense location
USA
and
in a configure configuration rules, you
need to enter this location, per diem
option, currency code US dollars, daily
rate as an option and for example, $100
as amount and it will work automatically
in the background.
So, what else you need to set up to
start using
expense management in the Business
Central?
You need to start with expense agent
setup.
Expense agent setup even if you do not
want to use agent, this is the name of
page where you will have and find
primary setup for many different
options. I will show you in a demo. Then
you have expense payment methods where
you will choose what will be
reimbursement type. That means if you
paid as a cash by employee paid or with
private credit card or you paid with a
company card or a company paid through
bank account. So, in the first option,
if employee paid with his own money,
this is reimbursable because this
employee needs to get money back from a
company. In other option, they are
allowed to have credit card company
credit card or bank account paid. But in
this case, it will be expensed but not
reimbursed because company will already
cover these amounts.
So, you have expense locations, expense
management rules and then for each of
expense, you need to prepare expense
categories and to make a setup if these
categories require itemization,
participants,
per diem, mileage and so on. And
eventually add subcategories where this
is needed
and expense groups.
For posting
you you will use
two different posting groups. Expense
posting groups for lines. So, how you
will post expense and employee posting
groups for header.
So, this is what we have right now in a
setup and
Before I continue, I want just to with
the demo, I just wanted to explain I
mentioned reimbursable reimbursable
amount is if
employee will get money back or not. But
there is another option if this is a
refundable.
So, refundable versus reimbursable.
First, we need to cover
refundable.
So, any expense if compliant based on
company rules is refundable expense.
Default value on expense category
subcategory will be for example,
refundable and it will be provided
directly to any expense or expense
report lines. But you can modify. And
even if you have non-refundable
uh, type, you can in some specific
situation, if you have permissions, you
can change to, uh, refundable.
So,
uh, important is that non-refundable
expenses will not be posted to the
general, uh, ledger. This is not
refundable. But why do we have it? It
can happen that, uh, you will use
company card and spend some amount on
some, uh, expense what is not, uh,
refundable. This is not allowed by
company policy, but you already spent
it. So, you must post this information
and that means that actually you need to
require this money back from employee
because employee spent amount not
allowed by the company. Or, uh, we will
get, uh, receipt and on receipts you
will have four lines, three lines are
refundable, one line is not refundable.
So, uh, employee will be will be
reimbursed only partially. So, this is
important to have refundable
non-refundable because you you can have
different combinations there.
And plus,
sometimes employee doesn't know if this
is refundable or not. They will scan
receipt, create expense, they don't
know, and later it can be, uh,
signalized that this expense is not
refundable, so you will not get money,
you will not be paid for this, uh,
expense. So, there are a lot of reasons
why we need to have, even if not
refundable, why we not why we need to
have this in the system. But now, if
this is refundable, we have reimbursable
and this is what I mentioned. If
employee paid his own money, he will or
[snorts] she will, they will get this
money back. If they spend, uh, money
from company card or bank account, this
is refundable but not reimbursable. You
still need to register this expense
report, so you will have properly, uh,
posted expense account.
So, this is important to understand.
Okay. Now, let's look into demo.
I will start with a,
uh, first expense
agent setup.
As I said, this is the first place what
you need to set up.
Okay. This is the place where you can
enable agent and, uh, as I said, this is
not now about agent, I will show, uh,
everything outside of agent. So, you can
choose a many of options. I will not
show all of them, but some of important.
For example, if you have different
currencies, exchange, uh, rate for
expenses can be expense date or posting
date.
Or if, uh, prepayment, uh, is allowed or
not.
>> [snorts]
>> So, when to create, uh,
expense reports. And you can find about
rounding, some other options here. When
receipt number is mandatory because you
will register receipt, but if receipt
number is mandatory or not. If you say
yes, you cannot create expense without,
uh, receipt. Or merchant, uh, name is
mandatory or not. So, again, this is on
you, you can say this is mandatory or
not.
It depends how, uh, you want to set up.
Then, you have these rules in the
system.
And number series, of course. Now, this
allowance, this is much more com- it can
be much more complicated. Even not not
about, uh, how many fields we have, but,
uh, what is an impact. You have standard
rate of mileage. This is if when you are
using your private,
uh, car for company purpose, for
business purpose, you you will get
reimbursed for this, uh, amount
multiplied with, uh, kilometers or miles
you used. Then, we have per diem
calculation. How we will use per diem
calculation? Different rules, different
authorities, different countries,
different, uh, per diem calculations.
So, you have none because in some
countries you do not calculate per diem
because you will reimburse, for example,
employee for meals for for what they,
uh, really can, uh,
uh, provide as a receipt, but you can
choose option full calendar day. And
what does it mean? Only if you spend
full day from the first minute until the
last minute of the day, you will be
reimbursed. Or overnight stay, that
means only if you spend night, uh,
regardless if you spend 23 hours,
uh, from 1:00 a.m. until the midnight,
if you but not stay overnight, you will
not be reimbursed. Or, the probably the
most popular 24 rolling period. What
does it mean? From the moment when I
started my, uh, trip, every 24 hours I
will have one full per per diem
calculated. But what else?
Uh, minimum hours for per diem. We can
say, "Okay, yes for 24, but what if I
have
17 or 19 hours? Is this per diem or
not?" So, you can configure here what is
minimum amount for full per diem. So, if
you spend less, in this case than 12
hours, you will not be reimbursed. But
if you spend 14 hours, it will be
treated as a full per diem. And then,
plus on top of that, you have sometimes
you didn't spend 12 hours, but you have
you are eligible for partially, uh, to
get, uh,
per diem. So, now you have partial day
rules. Again, you have flat percentage
of, uh, full rate or based on eligible
hours. If you choose based on eligible
hours, you need to say minimum amount of
hours. So,
what does it mean?
Uh, 12 or more hours you will get full
per diem. Between 8 and 12, you will get
partial per diem. Less than 8 hours, you
will not be reimbursed. And now,
what is this partially per diem? You can
configure what is the percent, 60%. And
now, we have some reduction. Okay, you
will be reimbursed for your per diem,
but company, uh, maybe will uh, will,
uh, decrease this amount if you already
have, uh, receipt for lunch or for
dinner because if you already have
included in the hotel stay, you will not
go you will not get full reimbursement.
So, now, for example, I have zero
reduction for breakfast, but I I have
30% for lunch and 20% for dinner.
So, there are a lot of another, uh,
options for setting up. I will not show,
as I said, all of them. What else is
important? Expense users. You need to
have expense user created for all your
uh,
users in the system.
Uh, additional they need to be connected
with employees because we need to
collect employee posting group for all
these employees.
Then,
what else we have? We have expense
categories. This is what I mentioned. We
have airline ticket, car, courier,
entertainment, so on. For example, if I
open hotel,
it require itemization. What does it
mean? You need to provide all details
about your hotel stay. So, this is not
enough to have only one,
uh, amount, one line. You need to
provide, uh, how many days you spend
there, uh, to itemize each line,
breakfast, uh, room service, whatever
you spend in the hotel stay.
You can change
to none if you do not need it, but you
can keep itemizing. You can use
participants. So, for example, if you
have business lunch, business dinner,
you are supposed to provide a list of
names, uh, together with you. So, you
need to provide participants. Then, per
diem,
this is a signal for system that this
expense category should calculate per
diem based on rules I just explained.
And mileage for calculation. Then, for
almost all of them you will have this
refundable. What else is important? You
have posting groups. I will explain more
about posting groups. And attachment
enforcement. You can say, "I don't need
attachment." Or you can provide warning
or error if there is no attachment. I
keep here right now with the warnings.
Then, default payment method. This is
what I mentioned.
Uh, you can see,
uh, I have here credit card, but you can
have cash or some other options.
Uh,
sorry, I wanted
full list. So, you have company
reimbursement type, credit card, and
employee. So, you can configure uh,
different expense payment methods here.
Uh, all these payment methods are only
default methods when you start to work
with expenses.
And expense group, this is not
mandatory, but it will be a much easier
to,
uh, later when you want to analyze all
your details in expense, uh, entries to
find groups to get better information.
Now, let's look into subcategories.
Subcategories are not necessary, but if
you are require itemization, you must
have subcategories. And, uh, that that
means that you will have itemization
based on these subcategories. Some of
these, uh, expense,
uh, subcategories can require, for
example, different description. I want
if you use hotel parking, I want to
override this default description with,
uh, all these details why you use the
parking. Or, you can set up if they are
refundable or not. For example, hotel
incident is not refundable. Room service
or mini bar are not both of them are not
refundable. So, you can configure, uh,
when you have itemization and
subcategories much more into details
that one receipt can be partially, uh,
refundable partially not.
And
I said I need to explain you expense
posting groups. We have expense posting
groups, we have prepayment, we have
refundable debit amount, and rounding,
uh, amounts as well. So, you can
configure posting groups and you can use
employee posting groups
for header postings. So, you have
additional options here. Uh, expense
report payable account, expense report
prepayment account, so you can configure
how system will post all details from
the header.
So, this is basic, uh, setup. Uh, I said
we have a few more things, expense
location.
So, you have different examples here,
So, I will open UK other. So, that means
everything in the UK except London.
You have different expense location card
if this is London. So, now you can if
this is one
post number
code you can use a London for here but
London you can find a lot of different.
So, you can use as a city or you can
enter here as a state or province London
area. So, this is on you. You can make
all these different combinations but
once you have set up all these expense
locations, what is important you need to
configure expense management rules.
And then you will find for example here
for UK other
per diems category expense location UK
other
GBP as a currency code and daily rate
115. When I move to
sorry, another direction
to UK London, I have
everything the same per diem but this
time UK London GBP daily rate 140. So,
you can configure your daily rate
based on what you want to use.
And for example, you can configure
entertainment event
that you are for example allowed to
spend more than 500 but only if you at
least have justification provided. But
1,000 is maximum amount so you cannot
spend more than 1,000. So, you have many
different rules you can use here as
well.
So, now I will show you expenses.
Even if I mentioned expenses are not
possible to be used if you are using
Business Central outside of agent. But
why I want to show you? Because when you
are using agent
you can handle in a Business Central as
well. So, you will sometimes open this
environments if you have Business
Central license so you need to have team
member license to open it. But that
means if you have something in expense
table,
you have activated expense agent.
So, you cannot create new one but you
can modify.
As for example, I have already two
expense reports submitted. One released
um
uh expense
what is about airline ticket. So, I have
all this information here.
And then I will look what I have opened.
So, this is already created from
let's say by
uh
assuming already created by expense
agent but you can modify this in the
Business Central. So, I have
um
description.
I do not have uh merchant name. I will
say Contoso
hotel.
And um
Okay, attachment are missing in expense.
That means if you remember I set it up
to have warning. So, I have warning. I
do not have violation. This is not error
but I supposed to use. And now I want to
show you here a few more features.
First
if this is a refundable and pay by card,
you will see reimbursed amount is zero
because you already pay by company card.
But if you change to cash, you will see
that this amount 1,000 you are supposed
to be paid 1,000 as well.
So, that that's that's fine.
Then
if this is not refundable
you can just switch this and it will be
excluded from
this calculation.
So, there these few options. But what
else we can do? We can connect this
expense
to specific project.
So, I can easily add okay, this is
project and this is project task number.
So, I can easily connect and it will be
automatically added into project
ledger entry. Or
maybe this is billable to your customer.
So, you may this expense on behalf of
your company but you can
invoice to your customer. So, you can
mark billable and then you can choose
your customer you want to to create
receipt to create invoice. So, system
will automatically when you post expense
report create sales invoice to this
customer as well. So, there are a lot of
other options.
I will remove right now all of them. Of
course, dimensions are here and I will
release.
So, I will switch to another.
I have mileage here just to show
example. I have starting point, ending
point and some number of kilometers or
miles regardless and system will
automatically calculate
if you remember 1.2 multiply 120. This
is 144.
So, that's fine. It will be amount will
be reimbursed.
Okay, release.
What else I have?
Moral event.
So, now okay, I pay by card and what I
want to add, I want to add participant.
This is what I mentioned. I need to have
guests and guests can be employee or can
be external employee. I have some
external employee. I will not point all
details. So, I have employee from my
employee table and I can add external
employees with all these details. So,
once then I have all my participant, all
good. I can just add dimensions because
I didn't have a default and I can
release.
And
now what else I have per diem.
This is now interesting because
I
have for example, you can see in GBP 575
per diem. And how system calculate is
starting date and time, ending date
time. So, system recalculated what is
exact amount and this is in pounds. But
because this is in US dollar database,
this is Cronus USA. System automatically
recalculated to US dollars so you will
be reimbursed in US dollars and this is
371.34
based on currency system in the in the
system.
So, we have all this information inside.
What else we can do? If you have per
diem, you can see we have interactive
this
action. It depends on
expense category setup. So, if this is
for example hotel, it will require
itemization. If this is entertainment
event, it will require participant. As
this is per diem, it will require
additional per diem information. So, now
you can see based on this starting date
and time system calculated for each of
day full per diem.
And now I can say for this
second day I had dinner so you can see
reduced and for this day I had lunch.
So, adding where you had a dinner lunch,
system will recalculate and then you
will see that different amount, reversal
amount and different recalculated to US
dollars.
Okay, I can say release this as well.
And okay, I finished with all expenses.
So, this is
this is something you can work only if
you are using agent and you want to open
expenses from Business Central.
But if you
do not use
expense
agent
you can start with expense reports.
Now I will create expense report for all
these existing expenses.
If you are using agent, it will be done
automatically but you can still do it
manually. Get expense lines very similar
process you have with get receipt lines
when you have purchase process for
example. Just mark all of them and you
will get all of them transfer into
system.
All of them recalculated. If you look
show more, you will find all this
information what is about and even there
total amount, total reimbursable amount,
some reduction and so on so on. Now,
this is important.
Total amount is total amount for
expensing but
the biggest part let's say 3,000 if I'm
not wrong will be paid by credit card so
you will not be reimbursed. And you can
see here credit card employee paid,
employee paid, credit card employee
paid. So, you will be
reimbursed only for amount you didn't
you didn't use company card.
Okay, now I can release.
But this is important to see that you
have this rule violations. So, you
cannot post because of rule violations.
Why you do not get some
warning like that? Because we are using
same rule violations connected with a
web app and other sources of
access
when you are working with agent.
So, do you want to post? Yes, I want.
Expense report is posted. I will open
posted document so you can see posted
document. You can find entries.
You can see general entry, expense
ledger entry. So, you have expense
ledger entry.
You have
employee ledger entry.
So, everything good.
And now I will show you
purely Business Central without agent.
So
if I'm Business Central user only, do
not have any agent, this is how I can
start. I can start with the expense
report. So, I can create one new line.
And
I can choose currency code.
Amount will be for example Danish
crowns, let's say 5,000
amounts. So, when you calculate it to
local currency in dollars, this is 540
484. Then I can use for example car.
What does it mean car usage, fuel,
maintenance? I have for example,
$89.
So, I have additional
hotel.
Let's say this is in euro.
And if this is
1,000
50.
Uh 1 1,250.
So, in this case, you will see previous
See, I didn't have itemization for other
lines. But for this line, it will
require itemization. That means I cannot
post because I You can see itemization
require and itemization must uh total
zero must be equal to
to uh completely expense amount. So, I
need to itemize. I will not go into all
the details, but I will just show how it
works. So, I will start I will just add
one line for
Imagine that 1,000 one day and breakfast
is extremely expensive.
250.
So, all good. It works. So, now
we do not have this uh rule violation.
We can add another options.
Gift, so on.
Uh ground transportation, meals and so
calculate parking, morale event. Again,
if I add morale event, I need to say,
"Okay, this is $800." $800.
But now I You can see I have dynamically
added participant. So, now I need to add
all my participant I had here.
As this is morale event, all of them are
internal. So,
now I do not break any violation.
Okay, you can post regularly this
receipt. You can approve and post uh
absolutely the same as the previous one.
So, there is nothing new, nothing
specifical. Only what is difference and
this is what I wanted to explain you
between agent and um non-agent scenario.
With agent, you can start with expenses,
but even when you have created expense
report, you can manually add expense
report lines. But when you start with
expense report and add
uh lines there directly, this is only
one way how you can do if you do not use
agent. So, this is only one way. And
after that, you can post regular
regularly, you can approve, there is no
any issue about it.
So, let's close this session.
Um I would like to invite you to watch
another sessions related to the expense
agent expense management from
introduction to expense agent, web app
for uh
for expense agent to web TC5 with chat
with the expense agent, new approvals to
expense agent, and
this one, expense management. So, all of
them together will probably give much
more light how it can work. And
on the end, don't forget to use some of
these links to get more information,
documentation, more communication,
especially now we have BC Viva Engage
enabled again. So, please use some of
these links. Of course, subscribe on our
LinkedIn page, go to our YouTube channel
to watch DC
um BC LE recording from this release or
for previous release together with some
other recordings.
So, that will be everything for today.
Thank you for watching this video.